MAN:
How are you getting on with the assignment on handwriting?
WOMAN:
Not too bad.
You know, I hadn’t realised that children benefit in so many ways from learning
to write.
WOMAN:
It’s such an important skill and yet most people think handwriting is less important than in the past
because people hardly ever write by hand these days.
MAN:
Yes.
And all the evidence suggests children should learn to write by hand before they
learn to type.
Not least because it helps their memory.
WOMAN:
That’s right.
The physical act of writing helps children to remember letters.
That seems pretty obvious when you think about it.
MAN:
What’s less obvious is how it helps develop their concentration.
They have to sit still and focus on one thing.
WOMAN:
Yeah.
That aspect of handwriting had never occurred to me before.
MAN:
Same here.
I’m not sure I understand how it improves children’s imagination though.
WOMAN:
Well, there was that study which showed that primary aged children generated more ideas
when they were writing by hand than using a keyboard.
I would’ve guessed that would be the case.
MAN:
Mmm, yeah.
I’d never associated spatial awareness with handwriting either.
I thought spatial awareness was more to do with knowing where you are in relation to objects
or other people.
WOMAN:
I thought that too.
But good spatial awareness is essential for writing because you have to space words
correctly.
WOMAN:
It’s not just fine motor skills that improve through writing as I’d always
assumed.
MAN:
Handwriting is so much harder for children with dyspraxia,
who have problems coordinating movement.
MAN:
It’s good there are lots of things you can do in the classroom to
help them.
MAN:
They need so much more support with letter formation – you need to play
lots of games to help them distinguish letter shapes.
It takes a lot of patience.
WOMAN:
Yeah.
I liked the idea of using one of those pens that lights up if
you press too hard.
That seems like a really simple solution.
MAN:
Yes, absolutely.
I’m not sure there’s much you can do about children with dyspraxia writing very
slowly.
MAN:
It’s more important to focus on accuracy and as they get more confident I
think they eventually speed up.
WOMAN:
One quite simple thing you can do is to use grid paper.
So they write each letter in a box and that trains them to space
the letters correctly.
MAN:
Indeed,
that’s more important for legibility than trying to get them to write in a
straight line.
MAN:
For some children it might be better to teach them to write on a
laptop rather than by hand.
Like children with dyslexia.
MAN:
They often really struggle with handwriting and some just give up.
WOMAN:
Yeah.
It’s not as frustrating for them if they get things wrong – on a
keyboard they can be more willing to have a go.
But I read that developing fluency isn’t any faster.
MAN:
That’s right.
Did you read that article on the benefits of teaching print rather than cursive
handwriting, where the letters are joined up?
WOMAN:
Yes.
Well in the past cursive writing was certainly considered more stylish and educated.
WOMAN:
But not anymore.
Teachers’ attitudes have changed because it’s been proved that cursive is more difficult to
learn – especially for children with learning difficulties who find joining up letters really challenging.
MAN:
I agree.
I was always worried that my poor handwriting affected my exam results.
And now research shows that I was right to worry.
MAN:
I’m sure a lot of students think it’s unfair that they’re being judged on
their handwriting not just their knowledge.
WOMAN:
Marks are definitely affected if examiners can’t read the script.
That’s why it’s always been so important to teach children to write
legibly….
WOMAN:
Do you think the role of handwriting will change in the future?
MAN:
I can’t see that changing much.
Touch typing still isn’t taught in most schools,
which is a shame.
But maybe that won’t be necessary in the future because people will also be
able to write by hand on digital devices.
MAN:
Anyway, teachers understand the value of handwriting.
It’s a basic life skill.
WOMAN:
True.
However, the fact is that people are writing by hand less and less
and relying on digital devices.
That does cause some problems.
MAN:
You mean like note taking?
There are lots of apps for that.
WOMAN:
And for reading historical documents apparently.
But my mum is shocked by my awful spelling and the fact that my
punctuation is really inconsistent.
I think you can put that down to lack of practice.
MAN:
I expect so.
Personally, I miss writing by hand.
I hardly ever write anything now.
I remember my grandparents had such beautiful handwriting and it was so individual.
MAN:
Nobody I know would be able to identify my handwriting now.
It’s a shame.
WOMAN:
I know.
I feel the same way.
I used to write a diary by hand and now I do that digitally.
It just seems less effort to do it that way.
So it’s not just a problem…